Guide to the Long Island College Hospital School of Nursing Alumnae Association records 2014.006
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Series 4: Photographs, 1858-2013; 3 Linear Feet in seven boxes of various sizes, one oversize folder, and 3.91 gigabytes of digital files
  - Graduation prom video slideshow - June 9, 2009 (Disk digital files, Folder -)
  - Graduation prom video slideshow with music - June 9, 2009 (Disk digital files, Folder -)
  - Graduation - June 11, 2009 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Student recognition / pinning ceremony - October, 2009 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Kingsborough Community College laboratory visit - April 15, 2010 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Graduation prom - May 26, 2010 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Graduation - June 8, 2010 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Student recognition / pinning ceremony, 2010 (Box 1, Folder -)
  - Yearbook portraits, 2010 (Disk digital files, Folder -)
  - Group class portrait (oversize), circa 2010 (Flat file folder 1, Folder -)
  - Graduation prom, 2011 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Graduation - June 2, 2011 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Student recognition / pinning ceremony - January 12, 2012 (Box 1, Folder -)
  - Student recognition / pinning ceremony - November 18, 2012 (Box 21, Folder -)
  - Nursing students and school patch, circa 2012 (Box 1, Folder -)
  - LICHSON: 1883-2013 slideshow (Disk digital files, Folder -)
- Series 5: Yearbooks, 1929-2012; 1945-2012; 4 Linear Feet in eight boxes and one folder
  The series contains LICH School of Nursing yearbooks, dating from 1929 to 2012. They were produced by nursing students and offer an overview of the year's graduating class, with focus paid to connections among students and faculty.
  The yearbooks contain a letter from the dean to the students; a section featuring faculty members (and occasionally administrative staff); a graduating class portrait; individual portraits of the graduates (sometimes featuring a personalized blurb); candid photographs of students during their studies, as well as snapshots taken during leisure time showing interactions amongst students and faculty; advertisements for local businesses; and dedications to individual students and the graduating class.
  Older yearbooks feature poetry and essays by students and faculty interspersed throughout the book. These feature thoughts and feelings on nursing and time spent at LICH SON.
  The centennial edition of the yearbook in 1983 is notable for the comprehensive history of nursing included in the beginning of the book, which illuminates LICH SON's place in nursing history.
  A few yearbooks contain handwritten notes and autographs of classmates.
  Please note that the series does not contain yearbooks from the following years: 1883-1928, 1930-1944, 1952, 1966, 1970-1971, 1989-1991, 1995, 2001-2002 and 2013.
  Arranged chronologically.
  - Yearbooks, 1929-1949 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Yearbooks, 1949-1954 (Box 8, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1954-1960 (Box 9, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1961-1963 (Box 10, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1963-1973 (Box 11, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1974-1982 (Box 12, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1983-1994 (Box 13, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 1996-2007 (Box 14, Folder -)
  - Yearbooks, 2008-2012 (Box 15, Folder -)
  - Yearbook Photos, 2006-2009 (Disk digital files)
    Digital portrait, IDs 2014_006_media_006 (70 JPEG files), 2014_006_media_007 (60 JPEGS), 2014_006_media_008 (164 JPEGS), and 2014_006_media_014 (3 JPEGS). Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
- Series 6: Newsletters, 1930-2013; 0.75 Linear Feet in twelve folders
  The series contains the following publications: Nurses Alumnae Quarterly (1930), The Alumnae Bulletin (1937-1938), NALICH (1946-2006), Scope (1955-1968), Team Talk (1970, 1974), Main Artery (1978-1994), Information Line (2005), LICHSON Newsletter (2009), and LICHSON Chronicles (2013).
  They represent the staff, students, and alumni experiences at the LICH School of Nursing from 1930 to 2013. Produced by staff members and students, the featured material ranges from campus events, to essays by patients at the hospital, to descriptions of alumnae vacations. This series presents a comprehensive look at a long standing teaching hospital in Brooklyn, New York. As the material begins in 1930, there is little to no information about the college from its founding in 1857 to 1929.
  Nurses Alumnae Quarterly features articles about general health, new laboratory facilities, the Biennial Convention of 1930, obituaries, an original essay by a patient, and class news.
  The Alumnae Bulletin was produced by the LICH Alumnae Association Publication and Press Committee in order to keep the students and staff informed about various activities of the Alumnae Association and the individual nurses. The Bulletin is formed from a compilation of the Nurses Alumnae Quarterly publication with additional items.
  NALICH was produced by the Alumnae Association as a detailed account of alumnae and their current situation in life, a update on the association's events, a call for dues to be paid, and any noteworthy happenings at LICH. It includes a letter from the President of the association introducing the issue and providing some minutes of past meetings.
  Scope was produced by LICH to provide information on happenings at LICH and the surrounding area. It features profiles of staff members, as well as the latest news reports on the hospital community. Noteworthy research being done at the hospital is also highlighted in the publication.
  Team Talk was published by the LICH Public Relations Department. These issues feature information about the opening of a new building, as well as general renovations. Information about staff members is also included.
  Main Artery was produced by the LICH Public Relations Department for hospital employees. It featured information about the different faculty departments with a focus on faculty biographies and special recognition for excellent service. Popular events are also listed and discussed.
  Information Line was a newsletter produced for current students at the LICH School of Nursing. The issue features news for the student body about campus events and other school related announcements.
  LICHSON Newsletter was produced by the school's Dean, Nancy M. DiMauro, in 2009. This issue is the first produced after a few years hiatus from any published newsletter for the school. It discusses the rejuvenation of the newsletter effort and a desire to reach out to the student body again and engage the alumni and current students in campus wide community events. Included is an autobiographical essay by LICH SON faculty member Irene Rempel.
  LICHSON Chronicles was produced by the LICH SON newsletter staff from 2012 to 2013. This issue is the final issue as the school closed its doors in May 2013. It features information about school events, activities, student and faculty accomplishments, and community engagement.
  - Nurses Alumnae Quarterly, 1930 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - The Alumnae Bulletin, 1937-1938 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - NALICH, 1946-1963 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - NALICH (4 folders), 1971-2006 (Box 5, Folder 1-4)
  - Scope (2 folders), 1955-1968 (Box 5, Folder 5-6)
  - Team Talk, 1970, 1974 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Main Artery, 1978-1984 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Miscellaneous publications, 2005-2013 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Series 7: Event programs and related items, 1897-2013; 1927-2013; 0.25 Linear Feet in ten folders
  The series contains programs and related ephemera for LICH School of Nursing commencements, anniversaries and reunions, and other events, dating from 1897 to 2013. It also includes five programs for the commencements and capping ceremonies of the Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing, dating from 1960 to 1962.
  Related material can be found filed under "Commencements and other events, 1945-1963" in Series 3: Subject files. Photographs of commencements and other events can be found in Series 4: Photographs.
  - Sub-series 7.1: Commencements, 1897-2013
    Four folders containing programs and invitations for commencement ceremonies and related acitivities of the LICH School of Nursing, dating from 1897 to 2013.
    Commencement programs: 1927, 1930, 1932 (photocopy), 1935, 1942, 1949, 1962, 1964, 1972, 1973, 1975-1980, 1982-2001, 2003-2010, 2013
    Invitations: 1897, 1949, 1969, 1978-1980, 1982-1983, 1991-1993, 1995-2001, 2003-2007, 2009-2010, 2013
    Class Day/Night programs: February 1953, September 1953, February 1954, February 1959, September 1959
    Commencement agendas: 1996, 1999
    Note: A 1961 commencement program is included in the "Bachman, David J." file in Series 8: Students, alumni, and faculty.
    - Commencement programs and invitations, 1897-1985 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Commencement programs and invitations, 1986-1998 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Commencement programs and invitations, 1999-2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Commencement programs and invitations, 2007-2013 (Box 2, Folder 1, Disk digital files)
      One digital commencement program from 2008, PDF file. ID 2014_006_media_003. Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
  - Sub-series 7.2: Anniversaries and reunions, 1953-2009
    Three folders containing programs and invitations to LICH School of Nursing reunions and anniversary celebrations, dating from 1953 to 2009. It also includes napkins from the 1963 and 1973 anniversary dinners, and stationary from the 125th anniversary of the School of Nursing (2008).
    Programs: 1953, 1957, 1964, 1967, 1973, 1976, 1978, 1983, 1995, 2008, 2009
    Invitations: 1957, 1958, 1973, 1975, 1978, 1983, 2006
    - Anniversaries and reunion programs and invitations, 1953-1978 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Anniversaries and reunion programs and invitations, 1983-2009 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Anniversaries napkins and stationary, 1963, 1973, 2008 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Sub-series 7.3: Other events, 1953-2007
    Two folders containing programs, invitations, and related ephemera for special events of the LICH School of Nursing, dating from 1953 to 2007. Events include Capping exercises (1953, 1957, 1958), an Annual Fashion Show (1957), the Dramatic and Glee Clubs' presentation of "Revue of the Romantic Nineties" (1958), Junior Senior dinners (1958, 1960), Spring Home Coming celebration (1971), a Eubie Blake concert (1975), Capping and Chevron ceremony (1986), Dean Joseph K. Davie's memorial service (1994), cancer survivor events (2001, 2004), and Pinning/student recognition ceremonies (2004, 2005, 2007).
    - Other events, 1953-2007 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cancer survivor events, 2001, 2004 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - Videos: "LICHSON: 1883-2013," "LICHSON: The Final Curtain," and "LICHSON:Ghostbusters" (Disk digital files)
      Three video collages set to music in two VOB files. ID 2014_006_media_011 (duration 18 minutes and 27 seconds, 12 minutes, 30 seconds and ). Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
    - Video of LICH Nursing Prom, circa 2000s (Disk digital files)
      Video collage of prom photographs set to music. ID is 2014_006_media_10b (duration 9 minutes 28 seconds). Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to access digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
  - Sub-series 7.4: Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing commencements, 1960-1962
    One folder containing five programs for the commencements and capping ceremonies of the Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing, dating from 1960 to 1962. One program for the 1964 joint commencement ceremony of the Prospect Heights Hospital Pavilion School of Nursing and the LICH School of Nursing can be found in Sub-series 7.1: Commencements.
    - Prospect Heights Hospital School of Nursing programs, 1960-1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Series 8: Students, alumni, and faculty, 1887-2014; 0.25 Linear Feet in ten folders
  The series primarily contains photographs, classwork, and diplomas of nursing students and faculty, dating from 1900 to 2014. Additionally, a class book containing a record of students' grades from 1949 to 1953 has been placed at the end of the series. More detailed information is provided at the folder level in the series inventory below.
  Arranged alphabetically by surname. One folder containing a class book of student grades has been placed at the end of the series.
  - Bachman, David J., 1959-1994 (Box 4, Folder 16)
    Contains programs for the 1961 and 1962 LICH School of Nursing commencements, a black-and-white photograph of LICH with a centennial banner (1959), a black-and-white group photograph of Bachman and students on a visit to Pfizer Co. (1959), a color photograph of the Hoagland building (1959), a print of LICH clipped from a newsletter (1973), a thank you card from the class of Feburary 1962, and a copy of Bachman's curriculum vitae (1994). See also the Memorabilia series for Bachman's cuff links and service pin.
  - Cosgrove, Miss, 1900 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    Student nurse employment letter
  - Dygert, Hortense E., 1887, 1983 (Flat file folder 1, Folder -)
    Diploma (1887) and related correspondence (1983)
  - Gaffey, Kathryn M., 1932, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 18)
    Contains coursework (1932) and one black-and-white copy print of Gaffey (originally taken in 1935).
  - Grass, Dottie, 1908-1909 (Flat file folder 1, Folder -)
    1908 University of the State of New York Registered Nurse certificate and 1909 LICH Training School for Nurses diploma
  - Hughes, Elizabeth, 1927-1929, 2014 (Box 4, Folder 19)
    Contains eight black-and-white photographs and two cards from a scrapbook assembled by Elizabeth "Bessie" Hughes, dating from 1927 to 1929. The photographs include candid shots of Hughes and other nursing students (including one of Hughes dressed as a man for a theatrical production), and the cards include a list of Hughes's classmates and poetry. The file also includes correspondence between Elizabeth's brother Ed with the LICH School of Nursing Alumnae Association regarding the scrapbook items (2014). See also the Memorabilia series for Hughes's rank and Class of 1930 graduation pin.
  - Morgan, Janet Potter, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 20)
    Contains four color photographs of the LICH School of Nursing Nursing Textbook Collection Dedication, featuring Janet Potter Morgan, taken on June 24, 2004. A commemorative bookmark is also included in the file.
  - O'Brien, Cecelia, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    Contains O'Brien's experience record book.
  - Ross, Elizabeth L., 1932 (Box 4, Folder 22)
    Alumnae Association membership card
  - Class book, 1949-1953 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Alumnae database and backup, circa 1990s (Disk digital files)
    IDs for digital materials are 2014_006_media_001 and 2014_006_media_002. Access to digital materials is available onsite at the Othmer Library. Requests to acccess digital materials must be made at least 2 days in advance by emailing library@brooklynhistory.org.
- Series 9: College catalogs, 1927-2000s; 0.25 Linear Feet in three folders
  Three folders containing college catalogs, dating from 1927 to 1998. The college catalogs provided general information on the nursing program to prospective students. The 1927 and 1930 catalogs include listings of students by graduation year. The series includes one LICH Graduate Training Program catalog (1963).
  - College catalogs, 1927-1965 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - College catalogs, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - College catalogs, 1981-1997 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Series 10: Handbooks, circa 1945-2005; 0.25 Linear Feet in three folders
  Three folders containing the following: Nursing procedure book (circa 1945), three students' handbooks (1956, 1959, 1979), a set of student rules and regulations (1960-1963), and "Notes on Nursing: What it is and What is it not" (2005).
  - Nursing procedure book, circa 1945 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Students' handbooks, 1956-1979 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Notes on Nursing handbook, 2005 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Series 11: Memorabilia, 1909-2013; 4.5 Linear Feet in eleven boxes of various sizes and two folders
  The series is divided into two sub-series: Printed material and Objects. Each sub-series is arranged chronologically.
  The series contains memorabilia and other documents collected by the LICH School of Nursing Alumnae Assocation. These include commemorative pins, nursing caps, promotional items, the school's accreditation letters, a congratulatory letter from New York City Mayor Ed Koch, school histories, and other items, dating from 1909 to 2013. Additonally, three nursing diplomas/certificates can be found in Series 8: Students, alumni, and faculty.
  - Sub-series 11.1: Printed material, 1933-2008
    - "The LICH and Training School for Nurses: 1858-1883-1933" (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Alma mater - lyrics and music, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 17, Folder -)
    - Marietta H. Madden (Class of 1928) letter to students, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 7, Folder 1)
      Formerly framed; page 5 only
    - Promotional items, 1960s-2000s (Box 7, Folder 2)
    - Gertrude Woods's 1927 advice to students, circa 1970s (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - LICH Division of Nursing report and tribute to Eleanor E. Harold, 1976 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Nursing: A World of Unity poster, 1976 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - Mayor Ed Koch - Centennial anniversary letter, 1983 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - LICH School of Nursing histories, 1983, circa 2000s (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Accreditation letters, 2003, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Laminated promotional clippings, 2005 (Box 17, Folder -)
    - Thank-you cards, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - The LICH SON Cookbook, 2008 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Sub-series 11.2: Objects, 1909-2013
    - Commemorative pins, badges, medals, and other items, 1909-2013 (Box 30, Folder -)
      LICH 50th anniversary medal (1909), Gertrude Sprague Smith Class of 1915 graduation pin, Marion McLean Class of 1921 graduation pin, Elizabeth Hughes rank and Class of 1930 graduation pin, School of Nursing badge (circa 1960s), David Bachman's cuff links and service pin (circa 1960s-1980s), School of Nursing pin (circa 1960s-1990s), LICH keychains (circa 1980s-1990s), LICH uniform patch (circa 1980s-1990s), service pins (circa 1980s-2000s), LICH Radiology pin (1992), 100th anniversary badge (1983), 125th anniversary badge (2008), and 2013 graduation pins.
    - Brass candleholder, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 26, Folder -)
    - Brass candleholder, circa 1930s-1950s (Box 27, Folder -)
      These candeholders were used during the nursing student's pinning ceremony
    - Nursing cap, circa 1930s-1960s (Box 24, Folder -)
      This cap was not worn by LICH School of Nursing students, and may have been acquired from another nursing school
    - LICH handmade nursing cap, circa 1930s-1965 (Box 23, Folder -)
      The LICH School of Nursing cap was designed by Ida Sutliffe in 1893. They were handmade by the mother of Margaret Keating through 1965.
    - LICH nursing cap, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 23, Folder -)
      This cap was not made by the mother of Margaret Keating, and is possibly machine-manufactured.
    - LICH yarmulke, circa 1960s-1970s (Box 25, Folder -)
    - Nursing degree and certificates (blanks), circa 1970s-1990s (Box 6, Folder 8)
      The two-year nursing degrees were first issued around 1970, and the degree in Applied Science Nursing was first issued in 1991.
    - LICH School of Nursing 100th anniversary commemorative dish, 1983 (Box 22, Folder -)
      The dish was given out at the 100th Anniversary of the School of Nursing of the Long Island College Hospital and the Nurses' Alumnae Association Centennial Reunion at the Sheraton Centre Hotel (Manhattan) on May 14,1983.
    - LICH School of Nursing 100th anniversary commemorative mug, 1983 (Box 29, Folder -)
      Mug was made in honor of the 100th Anniversary of the School of Nursing of the Long Island College Hospital and the Nurses' Alumnae Association Centennial Reunion.
    - LICH School of Nursing banner, circa 2000s (Box 31, Folder -)
    - Nursing and Asthma Walk t-shirts, 2005 (Box 31, Folder -)
    - Porcelain candleholder, 2007 (Box 28, Folder -)
      The candleholders were given to graduates upon completion of the nursing program by the Alumae Association
    - LICH 150th anniversary mug, 2008 (Box 29, Folder -)